# Talha Mahmood . Jarvis Consulting

Hi there! I am a York University alumni with a BSc Honours Degree in Computer Science. I am passionate and dedicate my unwavering commitment to whatever I set my mind to. As a result, I have been able to sharpen my work ethic to reflect the person that I am. I am a hard working, reliable, and trustworthy individual who is trying to improve every single day. Outside of work, I enjoy playing basketball with my team in our local Ahmadiyya Basketball League (ABL). I also had the pleasure of serving as President of the Ahmadiyya Muslim Students' Association (AMSA) at York University during my third and fourth years after I was elected by over 200 members. Now as an alumni, I continue to remain involved in our local community. Currently I am working and building upon my skills and experience with Jarvis as a Data Engineer Associate so I can continue to learn and grow within the Software industry.

## Skills

Proficient: Java, Bash, SQL, Agile/Scrum, REST APIs, Git, MVC Design Architecture, Maven, AWS

Competent: Spark, Scala, Hadoop, Hive, HDFS, Python, React, App Development, Jenkins, Docker

Familiar: Javascript, HTML, CSS, C, C++, PHP

# **Development Projects**

Project source code: https://github.com/jarviscanada/jarvis\_data\_eng\_talha

- Linux Cluster Monitor: A project that consists of a Linux Server Cluster Monitoring Tool which monitors the cluster resources and sends them to a PSQL database that runs in a docker container.
- Core Java Apps: Three java applications, a Java implementation of the linux command "Grep", an app that utilizes JDBC in order to connect to a PSQL database and manipulate our data as required, and finally a Twitter CLI Application that allows users to post, find, and delete tweets for their Twitter account right from our Application. It does this by utilizing the Twitter REST API and sending GET and POST HTTP requests.
- SpringBoot App: An online stock trading simulation REST API, built with the Springboot framework and utilizes MVC and Microservice design architectures. Stock market data is acquired by making HTTP calls on IEX Cloud's API and the application's data is stored in a PSQL database.
- Hadoop: Processed big data and built a big data platform utilizing Apache Hadoop and its components including HDFS, MapReduce, and Yarn. I provisioned a Hadoop Cluster on Google Cloud Platform (1 master node and 2 worker nodes) and then solved business problems using Apache Hive and Zepellin Notebook.
- Spark/Scala: The purpose of this project was to continue working with and processing big data, but this time using Scala and Apache Spark. I worked on various business problems with different datasets using Spark Resilient Distributed Datasets (RDD) and Structured APIs.
- Cloud & DevOps: Deployed the Springboot trading app on the Amazon Web Services (AWS) cloud making it scalable, elastic and highly available. The cloud services that I used are AWS's Elastic Cloud Compute, Amazon Relational Database Service, and AWS's Elastic Beanstalk. Also built a CI/CD pipeline using Jenkins to automate and fasten the deployment life cycle.

#### Professional Experiences

Software Developer, Jarvis, Toronto (2020-Present): Completed a comprehensive training Bootcamp on Core BigData technologies by industry experts and working on projects that include Cloud, DevOps, Java, Hadoop/Spark. Responsible for fulfilling Bootcamp project requirements at the discretion of product owner through agile team methodologies.

Web Development Intern, Homecentive, Toronto (Summer 2017): Contributed to data management and client database development initiatives in MySQL. Maintained website built on Bootstrap. Reorganized site content and improve layouts to optimize user experience. Tasked with training new interns as a result of outstanding performance in the first two months.

Junior Developer, Ahmadiyya Muslim Jamaat, Toronto (2015 - 2017): Contributed to the design and implementation of multiple Android apps built in Android Studio including a Quran app in Arabic and English Updated layouts and built new features. Collaborated with a team to develop mobile and web applications similar to WhatsApp and

implemented large data handling in JAVA, AWS, JS, PHP using Android Studio, Ionic 1, 2 & 3 Framework and VueJS. Helped develop and design web apps in Angular and ReactJS

# **Education & Academic Projects**

York University (2014-2019), Honours Bachelor of Science, Computer Science

- eFoods E-Commerce Web Application: Built retail app using JEE (servlets, jspx, tomcat, MVC), javascript, and derby for my final group project. Clients can create purchase orders after authenticating using an OAuth server.
- Unity Game Clones: Built multiple games with Unity including Flappy Duck, Pong, Stack, Chess.
- Augmented Reality Application: Built an augmented reality app that places objects (comment boxes) at GPS coordinates using ARKit

## **Extracurricular Activities**

• President - York University AMSA

## Certificates & Awards & Activities

- AMSA (Ahmadiyya Muslim Student Associate) of the Year
- Most Improved Player ABL (Ahmadiyya Basketball league)